the cream tends to be better tolerated
by men who are metabolically compromised
because of the different exposure to the
five Alpha reductase enzyme which is
often suppressed and the same thing I
think I can see with ssris like yeah
some people need ssris or snris or
anti-depressants I have seen
testosterone get so many people off of
ssris or anti-depressants or off of
diabetes medication like I can
completely agree with you because of
this stigmatization because
providers are so scared of it and people
are so scared of it one of the the main
things there's a couple things here and
because it's so stigmatized again people
are scared of it they use it as a last
resort when it should be the first thing
that they use for a lot of things and I
and I think any kind of metabolic
disorder right we should testosterone
should be used first um there's multiple
reasons for metabolic disorder uh you
know obviously lifestyle but a major
reason is our hormone levels so if
you're obese
if you're overweight and you have low
testosterone it should be the first
thing you track the the theory is that
if you lose weight that your hormone
levels will increase we find that to be
only true to a very small extent but you
know what else and what nobody else
talks about yes your total testosterone
will raise when you fix your lifestyle
when you fix your diet right but when we
fix our diet we're also reducing glucose
reducing the insulin sponse your shbg
will shoot up what I've seen is that
people actually their total testosterone
goes up because their shbg goes up and
your your hypothalamus reads the free
testosterone and that's what signals the
testosterone level if your total
testosterone goes up and your shbg up
there's no change in free testosterone
So you you're left with the same problem
so in my vast amount of experience
improving your diet making that
lifestyle change to increase your
testosterone is is a fallacy it just
does not work we need to get people
testosterone to fix their metabolic
disorder also get the dope imun energic
effects so that now we are seeing the
results from the exercise that we're
doing and and we start getting motivated
to build something it's a positive
reinforcing cycle that gets people on
the path and on the mentality to
actually live a healthier better
lifestyle and and the same thing I think
I can see with ssris like yeah some
people need ssris or snris or
anti-depressants I have seen
testosterone get so many people off of
ssris or anti-depressants or off of
diabetes medication cures type two
diabetes um I've seen it get people off
of blood pressure medications I've seen
it get people off of cholesterol
medications pain medications because
testosterone systemically
anti-inflammatory for a lot of these
things and I think that testosterone
should be the first thing that we try
instead of the last thing or not at all
and then of course when it is finally
decided to be used providers are there's
a couple things they don't understand
the pharmaco kinetics the phac Dynamics
of the routes of administration that
they're using so they use inadequate
protocols and they just don't use enough
they use very two lower doses and
inadequate protocols that they don't
understand the half lives and and and
things are wrong what similar things do
you see I couldn't agree more uh
everything you said is in in that little
snip was very very Akin with a lot of
the things that I've been saying
recently so first your point about how
free testosterone is what creates the
feedback at the hypothalamus this is why
this idea of a testosterone booster that
reduces shbg is just not going to work
because your body's just going to get
with the program um body's smarter than
you like the the body is way smarter
than any of us even understand so that
that's completely true as well and you
my my friend Dr Keith Nichols has been
campaigning for a while that
testosterone should be the Frontline
treatment for type two diabetes and men
and one I know one of the topics that
you wanted to talk about today was why
I've started to speak about the cream
more and I favored the cream more more
recently and it's because that while
testosterone is a fantastic treatment
for insulin resistance it's also insulin
resistance that contributes to a lot of
the side effects of trt as well um and
what what we found in my practice in my
clinics as well as other clinics that
we've partnered with is that the cream
tends to be better tolerated by men who
are metabolically compromised because of
the different explosure to the five
Alpha reductase enzyme which is often
suppressed I think one of the big issues
that people have even if they haven't
used things like five Alpha reductase
Inhibitors is because of this systemic
inflammatory load from being obese and
all the consequences of that they have
reduced 5alpha reductase expression so I
think a lot of the time we're dealing
with a 5alpha reductase deficiency
increase in prolactin pushes that down
more due to chronic stress and I find
that when someone is like severely like
you know metabolically compromised like
it dumps to Fire and they jump on the
cream a lot of the time they'll come
back with no side effects everything's
great no bloating no water retention no
moodiness no nipple issues nothing like
that even in the first few months which
i' I've found to be very remarkable the
other thing as well that I'll I'll also
throw in there is that I I think that
and I I often joke with my wife about
this I don't know anything about women
but I know quite a bit about men and
what I know about men's mental health is
that there are absolutely people like
you said who need to be on SSS ssris
snris antis psychotic medication
absolutely um they are a much smaller
subset of the people who were diagnosed
with major depressive disorder than
people would believe
and the problem with inflating serotonin
and I think we're potentially going to
find out about the cardiac ramifications
of that long term potentially when they
eventually look into it but the problem
with elevating serotonin is that it kind
of tricks your brain into thinking that
you're doing better than you are in life
and when you mute that discomfort I mean
if someone's going through a severely
traumatic event and the SSRI takes the
edge off so that they can take care of
themselves and get the therapy and do
what they need to do c great
but for people who have kind of gone
through life in a unhealthy vessel where
their metabolism screwed up their
endocrine systems not working properly
as a result they become very low
resiliency to stress they become very
avoidant their life becomes depressing
to live because they become fearful they
become less competent in their Realms so
all of these issues kind of Stack up
against them and then if you give that
guy an SSRI you're basically just giving
his brain a pacifier to go oh it's all
okay and I think people know that when
they're on these medications they know
that there's something wrong and they
feel empty whereas when you give someone
something that facilitates dopaminergic
transmission it allows the dopamine
system to work properly but it's still
mediated by a reward process you're not
just jacking it up for free or making
that system work the way it should then
now all of a sudden we're in a situation
where we're going hey let's make the the
work feel better which you know gets
thrown around a lot for good reason but
now it's also as you said as an
anti-inflammatory it also buffers and
regulates the effects of cortisol and
adrenaline so now we're in a situation
where we can actually push outside our
comfort zone and Take On The World and
do these challenging things and the
trajectory of where all these different
timelines can end up kind of like a
Marvel Multiverse kind of scenario is
massively different you know if
someone's on a different one of these
part start S at 30 and it changes at 40
because as you said this idea like you
know if if you have a guy who's got
optimal testosterone levels and then for
like a year or two he like gets into
like you know alcohol and junk food and
living on the couch then yeah maybe Dro
some weight he'll be able to recover his
levels they work 100% but if someone's
been obese like during puberty and
during development and that system
doesn't function properly because you
know juvenile obesity is a new problem
this wasn't a decades ago so if if you
were obese for decades or for your
formative years or you've never been
lean this idea that if you fix that that
your testosterone is just going to spike
up to an athletic level is just I mean
that's just asinine that's just coming
from but also you're in this situation
where if that did work then okay you'd
actually be able to get lean fit and
healthy but the problem is because that
system doesn't come back online you you
can't it's like pushing [__] uphill to
get the weight to drop it's virtually
impossible to get people out of these
hes so everything you've said is um is
completely correct and I'm a big
Advocate that and I made a video about
this a while ago is that you know I'm
not saying that everyone with depression
should jump on trt but I am saying that
if you're going to jump on trt or an
SSRI
like I know which one's going to be more
systemically beneficial number one but
two they say oh you know trt is for life
you want to be careful with that you try
coming off that SSRI 10 years that works
for you wow that was that was really
really well said and I had never thought
about it in terms of the effect of
having of increasing serotonin
artificially like that I I had never
thought of it from that context and that
is really good that I'm going to use
that that was a really good take and I
appreciate that a lot I'll just give
some more context on that so that I I
can give credit where credit's due
because I totally stole that from Jordan
Peterson um but in in his uh 12 rules
for life book I'm I'm going to butcher
but he talks about how lobsters have
this serotonergic system but I won't you
know give away the whole book people
should listen to it that the audio
book's fantastic but he basically talks
about how when lobsters are territorial
when they fight over you know food or a
mate or or or territory the one who
loses doesn't walk around starting
fights with the other ones because he's
he's lost the one who wins the fights
walks around and engages the other
lobsters but the problem is that if you
give the lobster who loses an SSRI he
goes around and starts fights with all
the other lobsters and gets himself
killed and um I I do wonder if if that
kind of Paradigm can really expand out
to a lot of people and I don't mean to
be harsh on on people's physical
appearances but a lot of the time the
physical appearance the manifestation of
how well you take care of yourself is
that if if we numb the signal when we
look in the mirror that we're not proud
of what's in front of us and that can be
anything from physical appearance to to
character to you know a whole bunch of
things not just on the outside I think
if we numb that discomfort it can really
do us a disservice because it kind of
makes us a little bit delusional and out
of touch with reality and I think we
need things to put us further in touch
with reality not take you would have no
incentive to change right to progress to
make changes right yeah that's really
really interesting I really I really
like that and that would show you why
working on the dopaminergic system as
opposed to the serotonergic system would
would be better in that case just like
we've we've both said I've seen so many
people thousands and thousands of people
get off of ssris because they started
testosterone and and just like you're
saying too I think it it's delicate it's
a delicate and then it's nuanced but for
a lot of people like they should try
testosterone first before maybe before
the test the SSRI yeah very interesting
so going further moving forward into
further like kind of issues that we see
with with protocols your use of cream
especially for people who are obese
especially to to mitigate some of the
estrogenic effects right and one of the
bigger things that I noticed that naves
and and amateurs seem to have is they
see they have a lot of questions about
estrogen and estrogen is like one of the
main Fields you I've seen you have to
forced to do so many videos about
estrogen because so many people are so
concerned about it and so worried about
it and kind of what I've started to say
is look if you have somebody who's
guiding you that's worth a salt then
estrogen isn't going to be an issue I
know how to deal with estrogen it's not
a problem yes you might get some
estrogenic side effects but I can
quickly mitigate those and I and I have
several tactics with which to do that so
I think one of the one of the problems
about people getting so many labs and
and wanting to see estrogen numbers and
just and being so concerned with
estrogen if you go to trt forums it's
like one of the main things that's
discussed and I don't think it really
needs to be again if you have somebody
guiding you who's worth their salt the
estrogen isn't isn't a serious issue um
and we can mitigate them and and your
use of of cream especially for obese
people yeah is is something good like I
don't have as much experience with cream
from the beginning I just started to
hear hear a lot of of people who
indicated that they just had better res
results the better absorption from the
injections better results um so I just
kind of started going to going towards
cream now with that being said I've also
seen massive benefits from The increased
F Al for duct taste production DHT using
creams and I tend to use a hybrid for
people who have energy issues or libido
issues or on testosterone and and we can
also use that to reduce the the
estrogenic effects as well so but what I
hadn't thought of and which I may steal
from you is for people who are really
obese to just use cream at first because
you know sometimes we're going to be
more susceptible to the aroma taste and
in the injections for you know for some
people can be really sensitive to it
again I have methodologies to deal with
it um you know a lot of easy first
things that we can do is increase
injection frequency reduce the dose
increase injection frequency find the
dose of testosterone that doesn't cause
these issues um and then and then it
usually becomes a function of people
getting used to the higher hormones
levels right we've evolved mechanisms to
deal with both high and low hormones but
when our hormones are low we become
sensitized to the hormones through
through several different mechanisms but
we're extra sensitive and then when we
first flood our body with hormones now
that's when we're having some side
effects or or that's also where the
honeymoon period comes with when we feel
really good in the beginning because
we're really sensitive to these hormones
and what I kind of try to depending on
how bad the side effect is I kind of try
to teach people is like for some things
let's just wait if it's a little bit of
water attention if it's a little bit of
nipple sensitivity that's not really
causing a problem their day let's just
that should AIT over time let's give it
a little bit of time
[Music]
he